<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>SBC on EETH - Blog</title><link>http://localhost:1313/tags/sbc/</link><description>Recent content in SBC on EETH - Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><managingEditor>jayeshjoshi08jj@gmail.com (hkcfs)</managingEditor><webMaster>jayeshjoshi08jj@gmail.com (hkcfs)</webMaster><copyright>hkcfs</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/sbc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The AI for Pennies: RISC-V SBCs with NPUs</title><link>http://localhost:1313/blog/the-ai-for-pennies-risc-v-sbcs-with-npus/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>jayeshjoshi08jj@gmail.com (hkcfs)</author><guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/the-ai-for-pennies-risc-v-sbcs-with-npus/</guid><description>&lt;p>You know, after talking about those &lt;strong>fat, hungry Nvidia GPUs&lt;/strong> that demand their own power plant and &lt;strong>All-Might Google&amp;rsquo;s custom TPUs&lt;/strong> that live in cloud mansions, you might think doing anything remotely &amp;ldquo;AI&amp;rdquo; costs an arm and a leg. And yeah, for training the next big ChatGPT, you&amp;rsquo;d be absolutely right. But what if I told you that the future of practical, everyday AI isn&amp;rsquo;t always about gigawatt power bills and million-dollar server racks?&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>You know, after talking about those <strong>fat, hungry Nvidia GPUs</strong> that demand their own power plant and <strong>All-Might Google&rsquo;s custom TPUs</strong> that live in cloud mansions, you might think doing anything remotely &ldquo;AI&rdquo; costs an arm and a leg. And yeah, for training the next big ChatGPT, you&rsquo;d be absolutely right. But what if I told you that the future of practical, everyday AI isn&rsquo;t always about gigawatt power bills and million-dollar server racks?</p>
<p>What if it&rsquo;s about a tiny, open-source chip, costing less than a fancy coffee, tucked away in a board the size of a credit card? Welcome to the wild, exciting, and sometimes frustrating world of cheap RISC-V Single Board Computers (SBCs) with dedicated NPUs. This is where AI moves from the data center to your desk, your drone, or even your dog&rsquo;s collar, all on a budget. And yes, it actually works.</p>
<h2 id="the-ai-dream-on-a-dollar-store-budget">The AI Dream on a Dollar Store Budget</h2>
<p>For a long time, if you wanted to do <em>any</em> kind of AI on a small device, you were usually stuck with an expensive Raspberry Pi or similar ARM board, maybe with a clunky USB accelerator attached that cost more than the board itself. But the scene is changing, and it&rsquo;s getting <em>awesome</em> for cheap hardware enthusiasts. We&rsquo;re seeing a surge of new, incredibly affordable SBCs, often powered by the open-source <strong>RISC-V</strong> architecture, that come with dedicated <strong>NPUs (Neural Processing Units)</strong> baked right into the silicon.</p>
<p>Why is this a big deal?</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Cost-Effective AI:</strong> Get dedicated AI processing for ridiculously low prices. We&rsquo;re talking single-digit dollars for some of these boards. <strong>Yes, even cheaper than that artisanal coffee.</strong></li>
<li><strong>Power Efficiency:</strong> NPUs are explicitly designed for <strong>inference</strong> (running <em>already trained</em> AI models) with minimal power consumption. This makes them perfect for battery-powered gadgets or always-on home projects where your electric bill is a real concern.</li>
<li><strong>Edge Computing:</strong> This hardware pushes AI smarts right to the device itself (&ldquo;the edge&rdquo;), reducing latency, improving privacy (because data stays local!), and cutting down on those pesky cloud computing costs. Your smart doorbell can see a package without telling <strong>All-Might Google</strong> everything it saw.</li>
<li><strong>Open Hardware Future:</strong> RISC-V is an open instruction set, meaning anyone can build chips based on it without paying hefty licensing fees to ARM or Intel. This fosters a Cambrian explosion of innovation and aggressively drives prices down.</li>
</ul>
<p>This isn&rsquo;t about training your own version of Stable Diffusion for free on a board that fits in your wallet. This is about running tiny, efficient AI models (like recognizing a cat, detecting a specific voice command, monitoring a production line for anomalies, or doing basic facial detection) right where the action happens.</p>
<h2 id="the-new-crop-of-cheap-ai-brains">The New Crop of Cheap AI Brains</h2>
<p>Here are some of the stars of this budget-AI revolution, showing what&rsquo;s possible for under $50, sometimes even under $10. Prepare to be amazed by how much compute power you can now get for pocket change:</p>
<h3 id="1-sipeed-maix-i-based-on-kendryte-k210">1. Sipeed MAix-I (Based on Kendryte K210)</h3>
<p>This board was one of the early pioneers, almost a &ldquo;vintage&rdquo; entry in the cheap RISC-V AI scene. The Kendryte K210 chip, found in boards like the <strong>Sipeed MAix Bit</strong> or <strong>MAix Dock</strong>, comes with a dedicated <strong>KPU (Neural Network Processor)</strong>.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Specs:</strong> Dual-core RISC-V 64-bit CPU (up to 400MHz), with a built-in KPU capable of <strong>0.25-0.5 TOPS</strong> (Trillions of Operations Per Second). It&rsquo;s got basic memory and I/O.</li>
<li><strong>Price:</strong> Often in the <strong>$5-$15</strong> range. <strong>Yes, you read that right. Five to fifteen dollars.</strong></li>
<li><strong>What it&rsquo;s good for:</strong> This tiny beast can run real-time object detection (like recognizing a face or a specific item), simple image classification, and speech recognition models. It&rsquo;s fantastic for learning AI on edge devices and for micro-AI projects.</li>
<li><strong>Where to find it:</strong> Check out the <a href="https://www.seeedstudio.com/Sipeed-MAix-BiT-Kit-for-RISC-V-AI-IoT-K210-p-4642.html">Sipeed MAix products on Seeed Studio</a> or similar retailers like AliExpress.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="2-milk-v-duo-cv1800b-risc-v">2. Milk-V Duo (CV1800B RISC-V)</h3>
<p>The <strong>Milk-V Duo</strong> is a truly miniature SBC that packs a surprising punch for its size and price, aiming squarely at embedded AI applications. It&rsquo;s often compared to microcontrollers, but with much more capability, running a full Linux OS.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Specs:</strong> Dual-core RISC-V C906 CPU (up to 1GHz), with a built-in <strong>Tensor Processor Unit (TPU)</strong> that supports INT8/INT16, offering decent AI inference capabilities for vision tasks. It even has a small amount of DDR2 RAM directly integrated.</li>
<li><strong>Price:</strong> Amazingly, often around <strong>$9-$15</strong>. <strong>A literal ten-dollar AI computer.</strong></li>
<li><strong>What it&rsquo;s good for:</strong> Running small computer vision models (think tiny security cameras, smart doorbells, pet feeders), IoT edge AI, or even as a tiny Linux server if you&rsquo;re feeling adventurous. It&rsquo;s a prime example of putting AI directly into a tiny, low-power footprint.</li>
<li><strong>Where to find it:</strong> The official <a href="https://milkv.io/duo">Milk-V Duo website</a> is a great starting point, and it&rsquo;s available from various distributors.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="3-luckytech-luckyfox-pico-bl808-risc-v">3. Luckytech Luckyfox Pico (BL808 RISC-V)</h3>
<p>Here&rsquo;s another impressive entry into the ultra-low-cost, AI-enabled RISC-V space. The <strong>Luckyfox Pico</strong> is based on the BL808 chip, known for its strong integration of processing and AI capabilities in a very small package.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Specs:</strong> Features a tri-core CPU setup: a high-performance C906 RISC-V core (up to 480MHz), a low-power E907 RISC-V core, and even an M0 core. Crucially, it includes a dedicated <strong>NPU (AI Neural Network Processor)</strong> capable of <strong>0.5 TOPS</strong> for efficient AI inference. It also has integrated Wi-Fi and Bluetooth.</li>
<li><strong>Price:</strong> Often found for <strong>$5-$10</strong>. <strong>Seriously, a single-digit dollar bill for an AI processor.</strong></li>
<li><strong>What it&rsquo;s good for:</strong> Ideal for advanced IoT applications requiring local AI processing, smart sensors, voice interaction, small computer vision projects, and anything needing combined wireless connectivity with AI on a budget. Think intelligent light switches or tiny smart assistants.</li>
<li><strong>Where to find it:</strong> Search for &ldquo;Luckyfox Pico BL808&rdquo; on platforms like <a href="https://www.aliexpress.com/w/wholesale-bl808-chip.html">AliExpress</a> or other embedded electronics suppliers.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="4-mangopi-mq-pro-allwinner-d1-risc-v">4. MangoPi MQ-Pro (Allwinner D1 RISC-V)</h3>
<p>While not always explicitly marketed with a dedicated NPU like its smaller cousins, the <strong>Allwinner D1 chip</strong> (featured on the <strong>MangoPi MQ-Pro</strong>) is a significant RISC-V single-core processor often used for multimedia and light AI tasks. Its capabilities are more general-purpose but still impressive for its class.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Specs:</strong> Single-core Allwinner D1 RISC-V C906 CPU (up to 1GHz), with a Mali-G31 GPU that can assist with some AI workloads (like accelerating TensorFlow Lite). It&rsquo;s a more traditional SBC with HDMI, USB, and Wi-Fi.</li>
<li><strong>Price:</strong> Typically <strong>$15-$30</strong>.</li>
<li><strong>What it&rsquo;s good for:</strong> Running a minimal Linux system, basic desktop applications, media playback, and light AI inference where the GPU can be leveraged. It’s a great platform for general RISC-V development and multimedia-focused edge AI.</li>
<li><strong>Where to find it:</strong> Look for it on platforms like <a href="https://www.aliexpress.com/item/1005003666014022.html">AliExpress</a> or specialized SBC stores.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="5-visionfive-2-starfive-jh7110-risc-v">5. VisionFive 2 (StarFive JH7110 RISC-V)</h3>
<p>Stepping up a bit in power (and price, but still incredibly affordable for what it offers), the <strong>VisionFive 2</strong> is a more &ldquo;desktop-class&rdquo; RISC-V SBC. It&rsquo;s got more grunt than the previous tiny boards, offering a much more comfortable Linux experience.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Specs:</strong> Quad-core StarFive JH7110 RISC-V 64-bit CPU (up to 1.5GHz), with a powerful Imagination BXE-4-32 GPU. While not a dedicated NPU like the K210 or BL808, its GPU is highly capable of accelerating many AI inference frameworks like TensorFlow Lite and ONNX Runtime.</li>
<li><strong>Price:</strong> Around <strong>$50-$80</strong>. <strong>Still cheaper than most new GPUs, let alone the &ldquo;fat hungry&rdquo; ones.</strong></li>
<li><strong>What it&rsquo;s good for:</strong> Running a full-fledged desktop Linux environment, more complex AI inference models (leveraging the GPU), and as a development platform for more demanding RISC-V applications. This is where RISC-V starts getting serious for general use and even light desktop tasks.</li>
<li><strong>Where to find it:</strong> Available from distributors like <a href="https://www.seeedstudio.com/VisionFive-2-p-5444.html">Seeed Studio</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="the-reality-check-no-free-lunch-but-a-cheap-one">The Reality Check: No Free Lunch (But a Cheap One!)</h2>
<p>Now, let&rsquo;s be real. These boards are amazing for their price, but they aren&rsquo;t magic pixie dust.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Limited Resources:</strong> That 16MB of flash or 128MB of RAM isn&rsquo;t going to let you run a full web server <em>and</em> train a huge AI model simultaneously. These are optimized for <em>inference</em> of specific, often smaller, AI models. Think &ldquo;does this picture contain a dog?&rdquo; not &ldquo;generate a photorealistic image of a dog chasing a cat on the moon.&rdquo;</li>
<li><strong>Software Ecosystem (Still Growing):</strong> The software ecosystem for RISC-V, especially with AI frameworks and specialized drivers, is still maturing. It&rsquo;s getting better <em>fast</em>, but you might need to compile things from source, dig through GitHub issues, or adjust configurations more than on a Raspberry Pi. It&rsquo;s part of the adventure!</li>
<li><strong>Learning Curve (Embrace It!):</strong> If you&rsquo;re new to embedded Linux or RISC-V, there&rsquo;s definitely a bit of a learning curve. Expect to use the command line, read documentation (sometimes poorly translated!), and enjoy the occasional &ldquo;why isn&rsquo;t this working?&rdquo; moment. But that&rsquo;s where the real learning happens.</li>
<li><strong>Inference, Not Training:</strong> Let&rsquo;s say it again for the people in the back: you&rsquo;re running <em>already trained</em> AI models. Training large AI models still needs those <strong>fat, hungry Nvidia GPUs</strong> in a cloud data center, or <strong>All-Might Google&rsquo;s</strong> TPUs. These tiny boards are the unsung heroes of deployment, not development.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="conclusion-the-future-of-ai-is-open-and-accessible">Conclusion: The Future of AI is Open and Accessible</h2>
<p>The rise of these incredibly cheap, NPU-equipped (or AI-capable) RISC-V SBCs is a huge win for open hardware and accessible AI. It means more people can experiment, innovate, and deploy AI solutions in places that were previously too expensive, too power-hungry, or simply too closed-off. From smart home gadgets to custom industrial sensors, the possibilities are literally exploding at prices you can&rsquo;t ignore.</p>
<p>So, if you&rsquo;ve ever wanted to dabble in AI on actual hardware without <strong>mortgaging your house for a GPU</strong> or paying <strong>All-Might Google&rsquo;s cloud bills</strong>, now&rsquo;s the time. Grab one of these tiny boards, flash some Linux (or even just an RTOS), and start making your cheap hardware dreams come true. It might be small, it might make you scratch your head a few times, but it&rsquo;s proof that sometimes, the most exciting innovations happen on the smallest budgets, and the most powerful tools are often the ones you can actually afford to play with.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>