<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Linux on EETH - Blog</title><link>https://eeth.pages.dev/tags/linux/</link><description>Recent content in Linux on EETH - Blog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-US</language><managingEditor>jayeshjoshi08jj@gmail.com (hkcfs)</managingEditor><webMaster>jayeshjoshi08jj@gmail.com (hkcfs)</webMaster><copyright>hkcfs</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://eeth.pages.dev/tags/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>BTRFS - the Best FileSystem</title><link>https://eeth.pages.dev/blog/btrfs-the-best-filesystem/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>jayeshjoshi08jj@gmail.com (hkcfs)</author><guid>https://eeth.pages.dev/blog/btrfs-the-best-filesystem/</guid><description>&lt;p>B.T.R.F.S., B-tree FS, Butter FS, or whatever you want to call it, I would argue, is one of the best filesystems, at least for me.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>BTRFS is a filesystem just like any other, but its features compel users to try it. This is what has made me a lover of it. There is a reason why Facebook (Meta) uses it, and Oracle used to develop it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of the best things I love about BTRFS is snapshots and compression, which I live by. No longer are the days where updating Arch (~btw) feels like terror about to strike or a new package or massive update (e.g., KDE5 to KDE6) can kill or break your system.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>B.T.R.F.S., B-tree FS, Butter FS, or whatever you want to call it, I would argue, is one of the best filesystems, at least for me.</p>
<p>BTRFS is a filesystem just like any other, but its features compel users to try it. This is what has made me a lover of it. There is a reason why Facebook (Meta) uses it, and Oracle used to develop it.</p>
<p>One of the best things I love about BTRFS is snapshots and compression, which I live by. No longer are the days where updating Arch (~btw) feels like terror about to strike or a new package or massive update (e.g., KDE5 to KDE6) can kill or break your system.</p>
<p>I have an old Dell laptop with 4GB RAM and an Intel Pentium N-something—not powerful. It cannot even play unmodded Minecraft at 30 FPS or any powerful game. It does not have an HDD because, when I opened it for the very first time (it was my first laptop, and I had never opened a laptop or fixed a computer before), I broke the cable. The HDD was fine, but that garbage cable is so damn weak. I could just blow air on it, and it would break. So, I installed Arch Linux on a 16GB spare USB thumb drive, which—even if it breaks—it does not matter, as it’s a small USB drive:</p>





<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"><code class="language-text" data-lang="text"><span class="line"><span class="ln">1</span><span class="cl">rw, noatime, compress=zstd:5, nossd, space_cache=v2, autodefrag, commit=120, subvolid=302, subvol=~~somethings~~</span></span></code></pre></div><p>These are my options on the HDD, which I primarily used for data storage. I have been using it for the last two years, and it has served me well since then.</p>
<p>The thumb drive runs F2FS with compression and some other optimizations, which I took for AI. It runs quite well, and my minimal install of Arch only uses ~4GB compressed with multiple browsers and LabWC—all the comfort I want.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Arch Linux - BTW</title><link>https://eeth.pages.dev/blog/arch-linux-btw/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>jayeshjoshi08jj@gmail.com (hkcfs)</author><guid>https://eeth.pages.dev/blog/arch-linux-btw/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;ldquo;I have been using Arch Linux for the longest time, and it has been a great system—or at least, that’s what I would say in a perfect world.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Arch Linux is like LFS (Linux From Scratch) but simpler. Since the introduction of &lt;code>archinstall&lt;/code>, it has become more&amp;hellip; let’s just say &amp;ldquo;dumber,&amp;rdquo; though it’s still quite a good system.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you want to learn about a Linux system but don’t want to waste 60+ hours of your life on Gentoo before binaries, it’s quite a good distro. However, I wouldn’t recommend using the &lt;code>archinstall&lt;/code> system. What’s the point if you do? I’d only recommend Arch if you know what you’re doing or if you’ve manually installed it at least twice with custom settings, like using BTRFS, custom repositories, or even Artix instead of Arch.&lt;/p></description><content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;I have been using Arch Linux for the longest time, and it has been a great system—or at least, that’s what I would say in a perfect world.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Arch Linux is like LFS (Linux From Scratch) but simpler. Since the introduction of <code>archinstall</code>, it has become more&hellip; let’s just say &ldquo;dumber,&rdquo; though it’s still quite a good system.</p>
<p>If you want to learn about a Linux system but don’t want to waste 60+ hours of your life on Gentoo before binaries, it’s quite a good distro. However, I wouldn’t recommend using the <code>archinstall</code> system. What’s the point if you do? I’d only recommend Arch if you know what you’re doing or if you’ve manually installed it at least twice with custom settings, like using BTRFS, custom repositories, or even Artix instead of Arch.</p>
<p>Arch is a rolling release, which means it doesn’t have defined versions like most software. It just keeps updating—and will do so as long as it’s maintained.</p>
<p>That said, it comes with its own set of challenges. If you want to do something unique, like running Linux from Google Drive (<a href="https://ersei.net/en/blog/fuse-root">source</a>), Arch Linux can handle it. Though, I would argue Alpine Linux is better for such cases.</p>
<p>All in all, Arch is a flexible, minimal, and community-driven Linux distro. People love it, and so do I. It has its challenges, but there’s a reason why I keep switching back to it.</p>
]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>