<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Gig Economy on EETH - Blog</title>
    <link>https://eeth.pages.dev/tags/gig-economy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gig Economy on EETH - Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <managingEditor>jayeshjoshi08jj@gmail.com (hkcfs)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>jayeshjoshi08jj@gmail.com (hkcfs)</webMaster>
    <copyright>hkcfs</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://eeth.pages.dev/tags/gig-economy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How Freelancer Company are Really</title>
      <link>https://eeth.pages.dev/blog/how-freelancer-company-are-really/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>jayeshjoshi08jj@gmail.com (hkcfs)</author>
      <guid>https://eeth.pages.dev/blog/how-freelancer-company-are-really/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a just an email but this is good enough &amp;amp; explaines everythign&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To: &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:youtube@rossmanngroup.com&#34;&gt;youtube@rossmanngroup.com&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;Subject: How Freelancer Company are Really - Sorry if that title is too generic/clickbate&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Hello,&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I have watched many videos of yours old and new &amp;amp; have always loved your work. I&amp;rsquo;m currently still in high school (please redact this), so my English or wording might not be great, and no, I do not want to use ai as it might be taken as spam.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is a just an email but this is good enough &amp; explaines everythign</p>
<p>To: <a href="mailto:youtube@rossmanngroup.com">youtube@rossmanngroup.com</a>
Subject: How Freelancer Company are Really - Sorry if that title is too generic/clickbate</p>
<p>Hello,</p>
<p>I have watched many videos of yours old and new &amp; have always loved your work. I&rsquo;m currently still in high school (please redact this), so my English or wording might not be great, and no, I do not want to use ai as it might be taken as spam.</p>
<p>My father works as a freelancer 10-20 years back it was a great job where people earned handsomely&hellip;.but now it looks like everything is taken granted for&hellip;.<strong>An complete AI model from scratch for $50</strong>, is this some kind of joke and no every freelancing sites are filled with 10,000 people competing for a single project&hellip;and the clients are getting used to this one of my fathers old client came up to develop an AI-tool for Note generation with image generation pdf, doc support and <strong>real time conversation</strong> &amp; a web gui with caching this was 4 months back at the time not a very easy take so my father quotes $300 the client after seeing this asks for to be done in $90&hellip;.how can a person survive in this as no company are hiring and <strong>client think to make facebook it will take you $400 &amp; 3 days</strong> &amp; the best part the client got a the freelancer told him can we work from outside &amp; after aggering he made some kind of a low-AI coded mess when the final payment was done&hellip;the client realised how bad it really was when something stopped working guess what the <strong>freelancer obfuscated the code</strong> the entire project was done for $60, a joke.</p>
<p>The freelancing sites themselves, once you make this mistake there is nothing to do my father does very niche work so not a lot of projects but the worst part is that, <strong>ALL FREELANCING SITE TAKE A MONTHLY SUBSCRIPTION OF $10-$40/month and even after that 10% or $5 from every transaction</strong> so a $6000 project the is actually $5400 and worst part of them all the clients has to pay $6606 so it is more like 20% and for that what yo get nothing&hellip;.My father did a project $90 to setup nextcloud, with custom theming, an email server and make the server secure yes all that for $90 &amp; at the very end when the job was completed the client told there was a mistake and told that we missed the deadline it was 2 AM my father told him that can we work tomorrow as it was very late for him&hellip;the client furious put a tantrum and then decided to ask for freelancer support and guess want we had to refund everything for free and gets to keep our work &amp; if that was not enough a <strong>2 week ban</strong>, guess what the client did not get any ban or suc in fact they made a new post to fix the issues in the current project for $2 when we told freelancer.com they just gave us a generic responce to stay out of trouble&hellip;this is how we used to make ends meal, after after this one inciden we have constant have been penalized for this now we fell like it is a daily routeen every 3 week -$150 and a ban for 5 days for some new garbage they made up.</p>
<p>It is now, i am writing you as we are not big in the tech world and you do have an audience, <strong>recently my account was suspended</strong> for no reason when asking freelancer they mailed use that you have violated the policy to many time, they deducted our months income completely for have outside transactions they didn&rsquo;t even bother to show use any evidence I am not sure in <strong>which country hiding evidence is allowed when you are making an accusation</strong>, and even had the <strong>audacity to charge our credit card now that is too much</strong>. I am very frustrated that how freelancer like my father have to struggle, hope you can shed some light to this also this is all on x.com/twitter on the profile BharatBjoshi <a href="https://x.com/BharatBjoshi">x.com/BharatBjoshi</a> please check</p>
<p>Sorry, if this looks like a rant but I am very furious at how these websites treated my father, if you want  I will try to collect evidence to share it with you.</p>
<p>Thanks &amp; Regards,
Jayesh Joshi.</p>
<p>Nothing more to add this sums up everything.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
