<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Router on EETH - Blog</title>
    <link>https://eeth.pages.dev/tags/router/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Router on EETH - Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <managingEditor>jayeshjoshi08jj@gmail.com (hkcfs)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>jayeshjoshi08jj@gmail.com (hkcfs)</webMaster>
    <copyright>hkcfs</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://eeth.pages.dev/tags/router/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>My Pocket-Sized Network King: OpenWrt on a 16MB TP-Link</title>
      <link>https://eeth.pages.dev/blog/my-not-so-pocket-sized-network-king-openwrt-on-a-16mib-tp-link/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>jayeshjoshi08jj@gmail.com (hkcfs)</author>
      <guid>https://eeth.pages.dev/blog/my-not-so-pocket-sized-network-king-openwrt-on-a-16mib-tp-link/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In network infrastructure, the prevailing wisdom dictates robust hardware with ample resources. Yet, the true power of embedded Linux lies in its ability to transform even the most humble devices into surprisingly capable network workhorses. This is the story of my unassuming TP-Link router, boasting a mere &lt;strong&gt;16MB of flash storage&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;128MB of RAM&lt;/strong&gt;, which I&amp;rsquo;ve elevated to a highly customized, secure, and performant network hub using OpenWrt.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Many would consider such hardware obsolete, quickly replaced by feature-rich, multi-gigabit consumer units. However, with OpenWrt, an outdated router transcends its factory limitations, offering granular control and advanced functionalities that belie its specifications. This isn&amp;rsquo;t merely about recycling old hardware; it&amp;rsquo;s about engineering a bespoke network environment on a shoestring budget of resources.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In network infrastructure, the prevailing wisdom dictates robust hardware with ample resources. Yet, the true power of embedded Linux lies in its ability to transform even the most humble devices into surprisingly capable network workhorses. This is the story of my unassuming TP-Link router, boasting a mere <strong>16MB of flash storage</strong> and <strong>128MB of RAM</strong>, which I&rsquo;ve elevated to a highly customized, secure, and performant network hub using OpenWrt.</p>
<p>Many would consider such hardware obsolete, quickly replaced by feature-rich, multi-gigabit consumer units. However, with OpenWrt, an outdated router transcends its factory limitations, offering granular control and advanced functionalities that belie its specifications. This isn&rsquo;t merely about recycling old hardware; it&rsquo;s about engineering a bespoke network environment on a shoestring budget of resources.</p>
<h2 id="the-hardware-underdog-a-lesson-in-resourcefulness">The Hardware Underdog: A Lesson in Resourcefulness</h2>
<p>Let&rsquo;s enumerate the modest specifications of this TP-Link device:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Flash Storage:</strong> A minuscule <strong>16MB</strong>. Every kilobyte here is a precious commodity. Package selection and custom firmware builds are critical to fit within this constraint.</li>
<li><strong>RAM:</strong> <strong>128MB</strong>. While seemingly low, for a dedicated router, it&rsquo;s manageable. However, the OpenWrt base system itself consumes a significant portion, typically around <strong>88MB</strong>, leaving roughly <strong>~40MB of free RAM</strong> for custom services.</li>
<li><strong>Processor:</strong> A low-power MIPS or ARM SoC, optimized for network forwarding rather than heavy computation. It efficiently handles packet routing but will bottleneck on CPU-intensive tasks.</li>
<li><strong>Ethernet Ports:</strong> Despite its other limitations, this router is equipped with <strong>1Gbps (Gigabit Ethernet) ports</strong>.</li>
<li><strong>Network Interface Anomaly:</strong> The primary onboard Ethernet port is non-functional, necessitating a <strong>USB-to-Ethernet adapter</strong> for wired connectivity. This introduces additional USB bus overhead and a potential bottleneck, despite the 1Gbps physical ports.</li>
</ul>
<p>This device was designed for basic home connectivity. Yet, re-imagined with OpenWrt, it forms the highly functional core of my network.</p>
<h2 id="openwrt-linux-reimagined-for-routers">OpenWrt: Linux Reimagined for Routers</h2>
<p><strong>OpenWrt</strong> is an open-source Linux distribution specifically engineered for embedded devices like wireless routers. It&rsquo;s not just a firmware upgrade; it&rsquo;s a complete operating system replacement that provides full control.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Linux Kernel Foundation:</strong> OpenWrt runs a full Linux kernel, inheriting its stability, security, and the ability to leverage a vast ecosystem of open-source software packages.</li>
<li><strong>Unparalleled Customization:</strong> Unlike vendor firmware, OpenWrt provides complete control, from low-level network settings to user-space applications.</li>
<li><strong>Designed for Efficiency:</strong> OpenWrt is built from the ground up for resource-constrained hardware. It optimizes for minimal CPU, RAM, and flash usage, making it an ideal candidate for this 16MB/128MB device.</li>
<li><strong>Robust Community Support:</strong> A strong, active community continuously develops new features, patches security vulnerabilities, and provides extensive documentation.</li>
</ul>
<p>Flashing OpenWrt involves replacing the existing proprietary firmware. This process is highly specific to each router model, sometimes a straightforward web UI upload, other times requiring more involved methods like TFTP or serial console access. <strong>Always ensure you download the precise firmware image for your exact router revision</strong> from the official OpenWrt website to avoid bricking your device.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Device Compatibility:</strong> Consult the <a href="https://openwrt.org/toh/start">OpenWrt Wiki: Table of Hardware</a> to confirm support for your specific router model and access installation guides.</li>
<li><strong>Installation Overview:</strong> The <a href="https://openwrt.org/docs/guide-user/installation/overview">OpenWrt Wiki: Generic Installation Guide</a> offers general steps for flashing.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="the-network-stack-sculpting-a-custom-environment">The Network Stack: Sculpting a Custom Environment</h2>
<p>Once OpenWrt is installed, the true potential of this hardware begins to unfold. Despite the stringent resource limitations, I&rsquo;ve implemented a sophisticated network configuration:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Custom VLANs (Virtual Local Area Networks):</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Purpose:</strong> VLANs allow for the logical segmentation of network traffic over a single physical network interface. It effectively creates multiple distinct, isolated broadcast domains.</li>
<li><strong>Implementation:</strong> I leverage VLANs to segment network traffic based on trust levels. For instance, I&rsquo;ve established a dedicated <strong>Guest Wi-Fi network</strong> that is entirely isolated from my primary LAN, preventing guest devices from accessing internal resources. Similarly, my <strong>IoT (Internet of Things) devices</strong> reside on their own VLAN, mitigating potential security risks should one be compromised. This containment strategy is paramount for network security.</li>
<li><strong>Configuration:</strong> VLANs are primarily configured via OpenWrt&rsquo;s network configuration files (<code>/etc/config/network</code>) and can be managed through the LuCI web interface. This involves defining interfaces, bridges, and assigning VLAN tags to specific wired ports or Wi-Fi SSIDs.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Network-Wide Ad-Blocking (Leveraging <code>adblock-lean</code>):</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Purpose:</strong> To eliminate advertisements and tracking scripts at the DNS level for all devices connected to the network.</li>
<li><strong>Implementation:</strong> Rather than resource-intensive solutions like <code>AdGuard Home</code> or <code>Pi-hole</code>, which are unsuitable for this router&rsquo;s limited RAM, I utilize a minimalist approach. This involves configuring <strong>Dnsmasq</strong> (OpenWrt&rsquo;s default DNS and DHCP server) to filter domains using <strong><code>adblock-lean</code></strong> (<a href="https://github.com/lynxthecat/adblock-lean">https://github.com/lynxthecat/adblock-lean</a>). <code>adblock-lean</code> is specifically designed for low-memory devices, providing efficient blocklist management within Dnsmasq.</li>
<li><strong>Benefits:</strong> This setup provides ubiquitous ad and tracker blocking across all devices (smartphones, smart TVs, PCs) without requiring individual client-side software. This enhances privacy, reduces bandwidth consumption, and improves browsing performance.</li>
<li><strong>Upstream DNS:</strong> Dnsmasq is further configured to forward unblocked queries to privacy-centric upstream DNS resolvers, such as Cloudflare DNS (<code>1.1.1.1</code>) or Quad9 (<code>9.9.9.9</code>), bolstering network-wide privacy.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="resource-allocation-the-art-of-precision">Resource Allocation: The Art of Precision</h2>
<p>Operating within 16MB of flash and approximately 40MB of usable RAM demands extreme precision in software selection and configuration:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Flash Constraints:</strong> The 16MB flash capacity dictates a strictly minimal OpenWrt image. Only core networking packages and highly optimized utilities can be installed. Any non-essential components are omitted during the firmware build process.</li>
<li><strong>RAM Management:</strong> With only ~40MB of free RAM, every running process must be exceptionally lean. This necessitates the use of C-based command-line utilities and careful avoidance of larger applications, dynamic scripting environments, or anything with significant background daemon overhead. OpenWrt&rsquo;s core packages are engineered for this efficiency, boasting small binary sizes and optimized runtime memory footprints.</li>
<li><strong>No Containerization:</strong> Unlike my NAS project, running Docker or Podman containers on this router is entirely infeasible due to the flash and RAM limitations. All services are installed directly as native OpenWrt packages, leveraging existing system libraries for maximal efficiency.</li>
</ul>
<p>Despite these severe constraints, the router maintains remarkable <strong>stability and responsiveness</strong> for its defined networking roles. It efficiently routes traffic, enforces VLAN rules, and performs DNS-based ad-blocking without perceptible performance degradation.</p>
<h2 id="network-performance-and-power-economy-defying-conventional-wisdom">Network Performance and Power Economy: Defying Conventional Wisdom</h2>
<p>The router&rsquo;s <strong>1Gbps Ethernet ports</strong> provide a theoretical throughput of 1 Gigabit per second. However, the reliance on a <strong>USB-to-Ethernet adapter</strong> introduces a practical bottleneck. While the adapter itself might be rated for Gigabit speeds, the underlying USB bus overhead can cap real-world performance, especially when multiple devices are saturating the connection or the CPU is under load from other tasks. For typical home usage, however, this setup still delivers robust and fast connectivity, often exceeding the requirements of most consumer internet connections.</p>
<p>Crucially, the power consumption of this humble setup is a significant advantage, especially in regions with high electricity costs:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Idle Power Draw:</strong> Typically a mere <strong>3-5 watts</strong>. This is the consumption for the entire device, operating 24/7.</li>
<li><strong>Max Load Power Draw:</strong> Even under heavy network traffic or when the CPU is active (e.g., handling many DNS queries), the consumption generally stays below <strong>7-10 watts</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<p>This translates to an exceptionally low operational cost over time, making it an economically and environmentally sound choice for an always-on network device.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion-maximizing-potential-minimizing-waste">Conclusion: Maximizing Potential, Minimizing Waste</h2>
<p>My humble TP-Link router, transformed by OpenWrt, stands as a powerful demonstration of what&rsquo;s achievable with minimalist computing. It proves that you don&rsquo;t need a state-of-the-art, expensive appliance to build a highly customized, secure, and energy-efficient home network.</p>
<p>This setup delivers:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Enhanced Security:</strong> Through rigorous VLAN segmentation and proactive ad/tracker blocking.</li>
<li><strong>Improved Privacy:</strong> By localizing DNS resolution and minimizing external data leakage.</li>
<li><strong>Optimized Performance:</strong> By stripping away bloat and focusing on core networking functions.</li>
<li><strong>Sustainable Computing:</strong> By repurposing hardware that would typically be discarded, contributing to reduced electronic waste.</li>
</ul>
<p>If you possess an old, seemingly &ldquo;obsolete&rdquo; router, I strongly advocate exploring OpenWrt. It&rsquo;s an excellent opportunity to deepen your understanding of networking, gain unparalleled control over your home internet infrastructure, and champion a more sustainable approach to technology. You might be astounded by the latent capabilities residing within that unassuming plastic enclosure.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
